Peterson Jr. Yuhala

PHD CANDIDATE · COMPUTER SCIENCE

IIUN, Neuchâtel, Switzerland



IIUN, Neuchatei, Switzeria

📕 (+41) 79 683 95 57 | 💌 peterson.yuhala@unine.ch | 🗥 yuhala.github.io | 🖸 github.com/Yuhala | 😾 gitlab.com/Yuhala | 🗖 peterson-yuhala-14009411a

"Be the change you wish to see in the world."

About

Currently a PhD candidate at the University of Neuchâtel, Switzerland, where I conduct research in the field of systems security. My work is more specifically on efficient confidential computing with trusted execution environments (TEEs). I hold a Master's degree in Computer Engineering from the National Advanced School of Engineering, Yaounde, Cameroon.

I'm a DIY enthusiast who loves tinkering with a Raspberry Pi, Arduino, ESP8266 or ESP32 and other electronics to build interesting automation projects.

Education

University of Neuchâtel Neuchâtel, Switzerland

PhD Candidate

April 2019 - March 2024

- Thesis: Enhancing security and performance in trusted execution environments.
- · Advisors: Pascal Felber, Alain Tchana, Valerio Schiavoni

National Advanced School of Engineering (ENSP)

Masters of Engineering in Computer Science

• Thesis: Memory address translation optimization in virtualized systems.

· Advisor: Alain Tchana

Sacred Heart College

Bamenda, Cameroon

GCE Advanced Level25/25 points (perfect score)

Sacred Heart College

Bamenda, Cameroon

GCE Ordinary Level

• 33/33 points (perfect score)

Research and Work Experience

Research Assistant/PhD Candidate

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

Yaounde, Cameroon

Sept. 2013 - Sept. 2018

Sept. 2011 - June 2013

Sept. 2006 - June 2011

April. 2019 - Present

March. 2018 - Sept. 2018

Computer Science Institute - UniNE

- Efficient confidential computing with TEEs.
- Adding TEE support in GraalVM CE for sensitive data protection in the cloud (collaboration with Oracle labs Zürich).
- Enhancing IoT security and privacy with TEEs and machine learning (VEDLIoT project).

Teaching Assistant Neuchâtel, Switzerland

Faculty of Science - UniNE

April 2019 - Present

• Networking and Web Technologies.

- Discrete Mathematics for Computer Science.
- Discrete mathematics for Computer Science.
- Computer programming for biologists (Python, R, Linux).

• E-Government Frameworks.

Research Intern Toulouse, France

Toulouse Institute of Computer Science Research (IRIT)

• Memory address translation optimization in virtualization systems.

Engineering Intern

Douala, Cameroon

Les Brasseries du Cameroun

July. 2017 - Sept. 2017

• Set up a sales management module based on Odoo ERP for wholesalers in the brewery industry.

March 20, 2024 Peterson Jr. Yuhala · Resume

Intern Yaounde, Cameroon

National Advanced School of Engineering

- Leveraging microcontrollers to build domotic systems.
- Implemented prototypes for home automation based on several microcontroller platforms: Arduino, MSP-430.
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/arduino-projects
- · Building programmable digital circuits with Altera FPGA.

Projects

Securing IoT data with Arm TrustZone and ML.

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

University of Neuchâtel (VEDLIoT project)

Feb. 2023 - Present

July. 2016 - Sept. 2016

- Porting hardware peripheral device drivers to OP-TEE OS.
- · Leveraging machine learning classification techniques to filter out sensitive data from data streams.

Multilanguage program partitioning for TEEs.

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

University of Neuchâtel (collaboration with Oracle labs Zürich)

Sept. 2021 - Dec 2022

- Developing a programming language implementation with Oracle's Truffle framework which provides generic AST nodes to encapsulate sensitive data (i.e secure values) in polyglot applications.
- Developing a generic taint analysis tool to analyse the resulting ASTs to deduce sensitive program portions which are partitioned into Intel SGX enclaves.
- See: https://gitlab.com/Yuhala/generic-tools

Making Intel SGX switchless calls configless.

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

University of Neuchâtel

Aug. 2021 - Feb. 2022

- Identifying limitations of the static configuration policy in Intel SGX's switchless call library.
- Building a dynamic SGX switchless call system which obviates the performance penalty due to static configurations.
- See: https://gitlab.com/Yuhala/zc-switchless

Partitioning Java programs for TEEs.

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

University of Neuchâtel (collaboration with Oracle labs Zürich)

July 2020 - June 2021

- Developing a tool to partition Java-based applications for Intel SGX enclaves.
- The program-partitioning technique leverages Java annotations and byte-code transformations to partition Java classes into trusted and untrusted components.
- The partitioned components are ahead-of-time compiled with GraalVM into native executables that run in and out of secure enclaves in a distributed fashion.
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/montsalvat

Secure and persistent machine learning model training.

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

University of Neuchâtel

April 2019 - June 2020

- Leveraging persistent memory (PM) to provide efficient fault-tolerance guarantees for applications running in TEEs like Intel SGX.
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/plinius

Memory address translation optimization in virtualization systems.

Toulouse, France

Institut de Recherche en Informatique de Toulouse (IRIT)

March. 2018 - Sept. 2018

- Modifying the Xen hypervisor to provide contiguous memory to paravirtual guest VMs.
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/xen
- · Building a VM placement simulator.
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/placement-simulator

SIMbox fraud detection.

Yaounde, Cameroon

Sept. 2017 - Jan. 2018

- National Advanced School of Engineering
- Developing a tool for SIMbox fraud detection based on the ELK stack.
- See: https://github.com/Yuhala/elk-fraud-detection

Publications

CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

Fortress: Securing IoT Peripherals with Trusted Execution Environments

Peterson Yuhala, Jämes Ménétrey, Pascal Felber, Marcelo Pasin, Valerio Schiavoni

. SAC 2024 (2024). Association for Computing Machinery, 2024

A Holistic Approach for Trustworthy Distributed Systems with WebAssembly and TEEs

Jämes Ménétrey, Aeneas Grüter, Peterson Yuhala, Julius Oeftiger, Pascal Felber, Marcelo Pasin, Valerio Schiavoni CORR abs/2312.00702 (2023). 2023

SecV: Secure Code Partitioning via Multi-Language Secure Values

March 20, 2024 Peterson Jr. Yuhala · Resume

Peterson Yuhala, Pascal Felber, Hugo Guiroux, Jean-Pierre Lozi, Alain Tchana, Valerio Schiavoni, Gaël Thomas

Proceedings of the 24th International Middleware Conference, 2023, Bologna, Italy

SGX Switchless Calls Made Configless

Peterson Yuhala, Michael Paper, Timothée Zerbib, Pascal Felber, Valerio Schiavoni, Alain Tchana

2023 53rd Annual IEEE/IFIP International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN), 2023

(No)Compromis: Paging Virtualization is Not a Fatality

Boris Teabe, Peterson Yuhala, Alain Tchana, Fabien Hermenier, Daniel Hagimont, Gilles Muller

International Conference on Virtual Execution Environments (VEE), 2021, Virtual, USA

Plinius: Secure and Persistent Machine Learning Model Training

Peterson Yuhala, Pascal Felber, Valerio Schiavoni, Alain Tchana

2021 51st Annual IEEE/IFIP International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN), 2021

Montsalvat: Intel SGX Shielding for GraalVM Native Images

Peterson Yuhala, Jämes Ménétrey, Pascal Felber, Valerio Schiavoni, Alain Tchana, Gaël Thomas, Hugo Guiroux, Jean-Pierre Lozi

Proceedings of the 22nd International Middleware Conference, 2021, Québec city, Canada

Talks

SecV: secure code partitioning using multi-language secure values

Bologna, Italy

24th ACM/IFIP International Middleware Conference

Dec. 2023

SGX Switchless Calls Made Configless

Porto, Portugal

53rd International conference on Dependable systems and Networks

June 2023

Enhancing IoT Security and Privacy with TEEs and Machine Learning

Porto, Portugal

53rd International conference on Dependable systems and Networks (Doctoral Forum)

June 2023

Partitioning Java Programs for Intel SGX

Zürich, Switzerland

Huawei Research Center Zürich

Dec. 2022

SecureL: Secure code partitioning via multi-language secure types

Rennes, France

EuroSys Doctoral Workshop 2022

April. 2022

Dec. 2021

Montsalvat: Intel SGX shielding for GraalVM Native Images

Virtual Event, Québec, Canada

22nd ACM/IFIP International Middleware Conference

Secure and Efficient Learning: approaches, techniques and threats

Neuchâtel, Switzerland

Conférence Universitaire de Suisse Occidentale (CUSO)

Dec. 2021

Secure and persistent ML model training with persistent memory and Intel SGX.

Virtual Event, Taipei, Taiwan

51st International conference on Dependable systems and Networks

June. 2021

Paging virtualization is not a fatality.

Biarritz, France

Conférence francophone d'informatique en Parallélisme, Architecture et Système (COMPAS)

July. 2019

Honors & Awards_

DOMESTIC

2018	Salutatorian, Computer Engineering class of 2018, ENSP Yaounde	Yaounde,
		Cameroon
2013	Valedictorian, Class of 2013, Sacred Heart College	Bamenda,
		Cameroon
2013	Ralph C. Okwen Award , Overall best high school science student, Sacred Heart College	Bamenda,
		Cameroon
2013	2nd Award , Brasseries du Cameroun Academic Excellence Award for a perfect score at the GCE A-Level 2013	Cameroon
	session (25/25 points)	
2011	1st Award , Brasseries du Cameroun Academic Excellence Award for a perfect score at the GCE O-Level 2011	Cameroon
	session (33/33 points)	

Social activities and community service

Scientific volunteering

University of Neuchâtel

- Organizing a STEM bootcamp: https://scienceprojectscmr.github.io/
- Writing scientific articles for LexTech institute blog: https://www.lextechinstitute.ch/blog

Scientific peer reviewing

University of Neuchâtel

- Artifact Evaluation Committee ASPLOS 2024.
- Artifact Evaluation Committee OSDI 2021.
- Artifact Evaluation Committee EuroSys 2021.
- Sub-reviewer IC2E21.

Conference volunteering

University of Neuchâtel

- Student Volunteer OPODIS 2019.
- Student Volunteer COMPAS 2018.

Skills_

Programming Languages C/C++, Java, Python

Systems Security Intel SGX, ARM TrustZone, OP-TEE

Web Development HTML5/CSS, JavaScript, SQL, Laravel with PHP, Flask

Miscellaneous Linux, Git, Shell(Bash), Docker, LaTeX

Languages

English Native proficiencyFrench Native proficiency

Interests_

Reading I love books on politics, economics, and personal development.

Sports Football, Biking **Music** Piano, Singing

Board games Chess

References

Pascal Felber

 Professor pascal.felber@unine.ch University of Neuchâtel, Switzerland

Alain Tchana

 Professor alain.tchana@ens-lyon.fr ENS Lyon, France

Valerio Schiavoni

 Assistant Lecturer valerio.schiavoni@unine.ch University of Neuchâtel, Switzerland